Guide to the Draper Family Collection 1836-1982 MC 11
New York University Archives
Draper Family Papers
1836-1982
MC 11
New York University Archives
2.5 linear feet
Several members of the Draper family, including John William Draper and Henry Draper, taught and held admnistrative position at New York University during the late nineteenth century. The collection highlights the genealogical history of the family as well as their roles within the New York University community.
Arrangement
Folders are arranged topically.
The files are grouped into one series.
I. The Draper Family
Scope and Content Note
The Draper family collection consists primarily of printed and published items relating to the Draper Family, its history and genealogy. Information within the collection highlights John William Draper as scientist, photographer, and president of the Medical Faculty, and also contains materials relating to members of his family associated with New York University during the nineteenth and early twentieth century. A significant amount of the collection pertains to Henry Draper's writings and other accomplishments.
Historical/Biographical Note
John William Draper (1811-1882) was a scientist, historian, pioneer in photography (credited with the first photograph of the moon, and one of the earliest of the human face), and professor and president of the New York University Medical faculty. Two of his sons were also members of the faculty at New York University: Henry Draper (1837-1882), who constructed a silvered glass telescope and invented the apparatus for celestial photography, and John Christopher Draper (1835-1885), professor of Chemistry and author.
Access Restrictions
Open for research without restrictions.
Provenance
The Draper Family Collection was accessioned and processed by the University Archives in 1984.
Draper, Daniel, 1841-1931; Draper, Henry, 1837-1882; Draper, John C., (John Christopher), 1835-1885; Draper, John William, 1811-1882; Draper, John William, 1893-; Draper, John William, 1905-; Jones, Theodore Francis, 1885-; New York University.; University of the City of New York. Medical Dept..; University of the City of New York. School of Analytical and Practical Chemistry.; American Chemical Society.; Articles.; Astronomical photography.; Books; Chemistry -- Study and teaching.; Correspondence.; Medicine -- Study and teaching.; Photochemistry.; Photography.
- Series I: The Draper Family
  - Biographical data on Draper Family (inclusive), 1981-1982 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Draper family genealogy, 1882-1981 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Biographical and bibliographical data on John W. Draper, 1878-1981 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - John W. Draper as photographer, 1894, 1950-1980 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - John W. Draper as photochemist, 1844, 1928, 1982 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - John W. Draper as President of the Medical Faculty, 1855, 1978 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - John W. Draper's association with the American Chemical Society; centennial of American Chemical Society, 1941-1982 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Obituary and funeral of John W. Draper, 1882, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Draper memorabilia, 1962, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - John W. Draper memorial plaque, 1935 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Centenary celebration of John W. Draper's birth, 1911, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Henry Draper (1837-82), son of John W. Draper, 1882-1981 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - John William Draper, Ph.D., specialist in English literature, grandson of John W. Draper, 1948, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - John W. Draper, M.D., great-grandson of John W. Draper, 1926, 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Dr. Daniel Gardner, grandnephew of John W. Draper, 1948-1950 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Henry Draper Memorial Centennial Symposium, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - John W. Draper Addresses, 1841-1873 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Draper, Henry. Scientific pamphlets by other authors, undated (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Draper, Henry. Inventory of tools, instruments, chemicals, and books, undated (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Draper, Henry. Memoir, from University Quarterly, 1882 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Draper, Henry. "Diffraction Spectrum Photography", Dec. 1873 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Draper, Henry. "Discovery of Oxygen in the Sun by Photography", Aug. 1877 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Draper, Henry. "On the use of Carbon Bisulfide in Prisms", Apr. 1885 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Draper, Henry. "On Photographs of the Nebula in Orion", May 1882 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Draper, Henry. "On the Construction of a Silvered Glass Telescope", 1864 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Plotkin, H. Colloquium at NYU Physics Department, Apr. 1881 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Symposium on the Orion Nebula to Honor Henry Draper. Annals of the New York Academy of Sciences, Volume 395, 1982 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Barker, George F. Memoir of Henry Draper, 1888 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Plotkin, Howard N. "Henry Draper: A Scientific Biography." Abstract and Bibliography of Ph.D. Dissertation, Johns Hopkins University, 1972 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence (about photography, John W. Draper as a scientist, etc.); 1839 ALS from Draper accepting NYU professorship; letters to and from Theodore F. Jones about Draper; other correspondence on miscellaneous subjects related to Draper and the history of photography, 1839-1969 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (about Draper Family); letters between Dr. Jones and John W. Draper (III) about the family's history; extensive correspondence between Dr. Jones and Charles Lennox Wright, a Draper relative, on the same topic, 1939-1949 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - John William Draper: Reprints and typescript articles. "Professor Draper on the Process of Daguerreotype and its application to taking protraits from the life," excerpt from the London, Edinburgh, and Dublin Philosophical Magazine and Journal of Science, v. XVIII, 1840; "Science in America" Inaugural Address of Dr. John W. Draper as President of the American Chemical Society, reprinted from American Chemist, Dec. 1876; and "On the Phosphorograph of a Solar Spectrum and on the Lines in its Infra-red Region," reprinted from the Proceedings of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences, [ca. 1880], 1840, 1876-1880 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - John William Draper: Lectures and Addresses. "Concluding Lecuture on the Theory and Phenomena of Heat," Medical Dept.; "An Introductory Lecture on Phosporus," Medical Dept.; and "An Address to the Alumni of the University.", 1841, 1847, 1853 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - John William Draper: Biographical Material. Photocopy of Draper entry from Universities and their Sons; typescript of Dictionary of American Biography entry, written by Ellwood Hendrick., 1900, 1928 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Henry Draper: Reprints. "On Diffraction Spectrum Photography," reprinted from the American Journal of Science and Arts, vol. VI, Dec. 1873; "The Total Solar Eclipse of July 29, 1878," reprinted from the Journal of the Franklin Institute for Oct. 1878 (2 copies); and "Researches on Astronomical Spectrum", 1873-1884 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Henry Draper: Memorial minute. By Geo. F. Barker, for the Proceedings of the American Philosophical Society., 1882 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Articles about John W. Draper, Henry Draper, early photography, etc., (photocopies). "John William Draper's Contributions to Astronomy," by Daniel Norman, Telescope V, (1938); "The Development of Astronomical Photography," by Daniel Norman, Osiris V, (1938); "Virginia Professor Put Click in Photography," by Pat Jones, The Record of the Hampden-Sydney Alumni Association, Spring 1967; "A Great Modern Observatory," by Mabel Loomis Todd, The Century Magazine, v. LIV, 38, n.d.; "Historical Note: Chapter XI: On the Process of Daguerreotype, and its application to taking portraits from life," no title, n.d. (includes part of an article from the London and Edinburgh Philosophical Magazine Sep. 1840), 1938-1967 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Miscellaneous NYU-related materials (photocopies). Course of instruction; reports to the New York State Assembly; list of "Philosophical Instruments Stolen;" and other related material., 1836-1922 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Photographs. Removed to LD 20, Draper Collection (Photo Area). Includes one glass plate spectrograph., undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Draper, John William. A Treatise on the Forces which Produce the Organization of Plants (Harper and Brothers: New York, 1844). (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - Draper, John W. Varia [collected lectures, addresses and reprints], 1841-1881 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Draper, John William. Textbook on Chemistry. Sixth ed. (Harper and Brothers: New York, 1851). Presented to the University of the City of New York by Daniel Draper., 1893 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Barker, George F. "Memoir of Henry Draper, 1837-1882." Read before the National Academy., 1888 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - The Record of the Hampden-Sydney Alumni Association, vol. 9, no. 1., 1934 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - J.S. Radway, Chemistry Notebook, 1876 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Draper, Henry. "Human Physiology", 1878 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Draper, Henry. "A History of the Intellectual Development of Europe", 1864 (Box 6, Folder 2)